Guide to the William H. Artz Papers 1971-1972
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
William H. Artz Papers
1971-1972
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 190
Artz, William H.
1.0 linear foot
This collection contains Mr. Artz's papers pertaining to his election campaign and his term as a delegate for the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention.
Biographical Note
William H. Artz was born in Montana and made his home in Great Falls. He was a certified public accountant and was named by Governor Forrest Anderson to a six-year term with the State Board of Accounting. He was active in organizations such as the Knights of Columbus and chairman of the finance committee for the Holy Family Parish. He ran as a Democrat for the delegate seat in the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention representing Cascade County and won.
This collection contains Mr. Artz's papers pertaining to his election campaign and his term as a delegate for the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention. It includes correspondence with the public sector and their opinions about different proposal that were being considered by the convention.
The collection is divided into seven series:
Series I: General Correspondence, 3 folders, 1971-1972
Series II: Amendments, 1 folder, 1972
Series III: Campaign materials, 1 folder, 1971
Series IV: Clippings and Pamphlets, 1 folder, 1971-1972
Series V: Committee Proposals, 2 folders, 1972
Series VI: Constitutional Convention Papers, 3 folders, 1971-1972
Series VII: Reports, 3 folders, 1972
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The materials in this collection remained with William Artz until donation to the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gift of William H. Artz, 1990.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana. Constitution (1972); Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972)
Cascade County (Mont.); Montana--Politics and government--20th century
Constitutional conventions--Montana
Montana
- General Correspondence, 1971-1972; Series I; 3 folders
  This series includes pre-election letters of recommendation supporting William Artz; constituents' requests for interviews with Mr. Artz; and questionnaires. Post-election correspondence includes petitions to Mr. Artz by other elected delegates who were running for office within the Constitutional Convention; letters concerning the organization of the convention; and congratulatory letters. Also included are letters from individual citizens, businesses, schools, and private organizations with recommendation for the new state constitution. Included are responses from Mr. Artz. These letters highlight the issues concerning Montana citizens during this time.
  Correspondence is generally arranged chronologically with some letters undated.
  - 1971 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/3)
- Amendments, 1972; Series II; 1 folder
  This series includes detailed amendment proposals offered by the constitutional convention delegates to the Committee of the Whole Amendment. These are suggested amendments to the proposals on constitutional revisions presented by the different Constitutional Convention committees (see Series V). The suggestions range from simple grammatical corrections to deletions of whole sections. There are indications as to whether proposals were passed or defeated. Some include vote counts.
  - Delegate Amendment Proposals, 1972 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Campaign materials, 1971; Series III; 1 folder
  This series consists of newspaper clippings pertaining to the election. They include reports on election results, expenditures of each successful candidate, party affiliations, biographical sketches, and advertisements. This folder includes the primary and general election results divided by district and subdivided by county. Also included are Mr. Artz's official nomination and membership certificates both signed by Governor Forrest Anderson.
  - Election Clippings and Vote Counts, 1971 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Clippings and Pamphlets, 1971-1972; Series IV; 1 folder
  This series consists primarily of newspaper clippings concerning issues that faced the Constitutional Convention and citizens' opinions. Included in this folder are a few articles and editorial opinions. Also included are a few instructional pamphlets pertaining to the Constitutional Convention. The newspaper clippings are generally arranged chronologically with some clippings undated.
  - Clippings and Pamphlets, 1971-1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/6)
- Committee Proposals, 1972; Series V; 2 folders
  The first folder in this series includes official proposals on constitutional revisions by the different Constitutional Convention committees. The first folder includes proposals from the following committees: Bill of Rights; General Government and Constitutional Amendment; Local Government; Education and Public Lands; and Public Health, Welfare, Labor and Industry. This folder also includes a clerical manual for writing a committee proposal and a few amendment suggestions similar to those in Series II. Included in the second folder are proposals from the following committees: Revenue and Finance; Natural Resources and Agriculture; Judiciary; Executive; Legislative; and General Government and Constitutional Amendment.
  - Constitutional Revision Proposals, 1972 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Constitutional Revision Proposals, 1972 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Constitutional Convention Papers, 1971-1972; Series VI; 3 folders
  The three folders in this series consist of miscellaneous papers pertaining to the Constitutional Convention. The papers include a few biographical sketches of candidates; minutes from meetings; polls and questionnaires; vote analysis; amendment proposals; correspondence; ballots; official rosters and addresses of delegates; delegate and citizen statements; newspaper clippings and articles; budget numbers; committee reports; a floor map of the convention in the second folder; a convention profile in the third folder; and other papers.
  - Statements, Comments, Suggestions, and Other Papers, 1971-1972 and undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Statements, Comments, Suggestions, and Other Papers, 1971-1972 and undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Statements, Comments, Suggestions, and Other Papers, 1972 and undated (Box-folder 2/4)
- Reports, 1972; Series VII; 3 folders
  The first folder in this series includes the final considerations of the Style, Drafting, Transition and Submission Committee on the various revised articles of the constitution and Bill of Rights. The second folder includes official statements of individual citizens (including the Mayor of Great Falls), and representatives of companies and organizations. The third folder includes committee proposal reports that were submitted to the Committee on Style, Drafting, Transition and Submission.
  - Order of Business and Final Considerations, 1972 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Statements, 1972 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Committee on Style, Drafting, Transmission, and Submission Proposals, 1972 (Box-folder 2/7)